A Guide to the Virginia Veterinary Medical Association Records, 1894-1983
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Virginia Veterinary Medical Association Records, 1894-1983
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1988-032
0.7 cu. ft. 2 boxes
Records--including meeting minutes, programs, bylaws, and printed materials--of the Virginia Veterinary Medical Association.
Virginia Veterinary Medical Association.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Virginia Veterinary Medical Association Records were donated to Special Collections in 1988.
Historical Note
The Virginia State Veterinary Medical Association was founded in Richmond on February 6, 1894, "with a view to the advancement of veterinary medical knowledge throughout the State of Virginia." The association was incorporated by the General Assembly two days later. At its initial meeting (March 22, 1894), the 12 charter members adopted a constitution and bylaws and elected officers, with W. H. Harbaugh serving as the first president. Through its regular meetings, the association provided an avenue for the sharing of knowledge among members. It also pursued legislation that would regulate the practice of veterinary medicine throughout Virginia. An amended constitution, approved by the membership in 1954, changed the organization's name to the Virginia Veterinary Medical Association. The VVMA continues to be active today (2013).
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the records of the Virginia Veterinary Medical Association. Included are such materials as meeting minutes, programs, and printed materials. The majority of the collection is comprised of a series of records books, presumably maintained by the organization's secretary. In addition to meeting minutes, the books include the organization's articles of incorporation, constitution and bylaws, programs, resolutions, correspondence, and speech texts. The collection also includes the minutes of the board of censors; a history of the association, written by Dr. George C. Faville in 1931; a handbook issued in 1981; and a few issues of the association's publication, The Virginia Veterinarian.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by document type, then chronologically.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Science and Technology
Contents List
- Records books, 1894-1953 (Box-folder 1-1-4)
- Minutes book, 1954-1957 (Box-folder 1-5)
- Board of censors minutes book, 1894-1945 (Box-folder 1-6)
- Constitution and by-laws, 1932 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Official registers, 1915-1922, [2 items] (Box-folder 1-8)
- The Virginia State Veterinary Medical Association by George C. Faville, 1931 (Box-folder 2-1)
- Handbook, 1981 (Box-folder 2-2)
- Programs, 1955-1959 (Box-folder 2-3)
- The Virginia Veterinarian, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 2-4)
  - vol. 3, no. 1, 1960
  - vol. 3, no. 2, 1960, [2 copies]
  - vol. 5, no. 3, 1962
- General records, 1961-1983, n.d. (Box-folder 2-5)
  - List of past presidents, [1956?]
  - Treasurer's report, 1961
  - Feeder calves, 1964, n.d.
  - Board of directors meeting notice, 1983
- Other veterinary medicine organizations, 1957-1961 (Box-folder 2-6)